China, like you say, you never know. I
mean, you wish that they would because I
think that could tip the scale. I think
that could bring about restraint um in
Israel. Um as long as businesses as
usual, Israel will not stop. So, one
would hope that China and Russia, you
know, the the the the bricks the bricks
alliance would intervene. We wish they
would intervene in the genocide in Gaza,
but for reasons, for some reason they
don't. None of them do, and I think it's
very sad they don't.
Hi, welcome back to Deep Focus. I'm John
Kuryaku. We are all in a precarious
situation right now visav Palestine,
Israel, and Iran. As the days and weeks
pass, it seems more and more clear that
Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin
Netanyahu is serious. He's serious about
a large-scale war against Iran and about
the concept of creating a greater
Israel. Look at it this way. The
Israelis are committing genocide in
Gaza. That's clear. And the
international community doesn't seem to
care enough to do anything meaningful
about it. while the United States simply
supports whatever Netanyahu wants to do.
And it doesn't matter who happens to be
sitting in the White House, whether it's
a Democrat or a Republican. Israel
launches bombing attacks against Iran,
killing hundreds of people, and at least
14 Iranian nuclear scientists, and the
international community just shrugs its
shoulders. Israel decapitates Hezbollah,
and the international community
applauds. Israel moves its military into
Syria to create some sort of a buffer
zone and the international media don't
even bother to cover it. Now we're
seeing reports that Netanyahu wants to
forcibly move all Gaza Palestinians to
South Sudan. That is literally the
definition of ethnic cleansing and it's
patently illegal under international
law. But things still can get much
worse. We're going to talk about all
this and more with our guest, the author
and activist Miko Pelid. Miko is one of
the clearest voices in the United States
on the issue of peace in Palestine. He's
the author of two books, The General's
Son, The Journey of an Israeli and
Palestine and Injustice: The Story of
the Holy Land Foundation 5. He's also
the founder and director of the
Palestine House of Freedom. That's right
here in Washington DC up on Capitol
Hill. Miko, thanks so much for joining
us. Sure. Great to be with you again.
I love when you come on the show. I
always learn so much and you always slap
down my optimism. So let's start with
Treata Parcy. Treat Parsy, the renowned
scholar, wrote a piece this week that he
ran on his Substack predicting that
Israel would attack Iran again before
the end of August. I'm having trouble
understanding why the Israelis feel that
they need to attack Iran again and so
soon. Israel and the US nearly destroyed
the Iranian nuclear program last month.
Israel killed 14 nuclear scientists.
It's clear that the Mossad has
completely infiltrated Iran. So why
attack again? What's the goal?
Well,
what was the goal the first time? What
was the goal at the time?
>> That's a good question.
>> It's about instability. And I think one
of the things people need to realize
about this entity called Israel that it
has been from the beginning and will
continue to be as long as it's allowed
to the source of instability in all of
Western Asia and North Africa. That's
what it has been. There's this myth that
was created that somehow the state of
Israel is an island of stability, an
island of democracy.
But if you take away the myth for a
minute and just look at it historically
year by year from 1948 or even pre
before 1948 because the instability
began with Zionist terrorist groups
already creating um the sense of
instability in Palestine itself. But
from that point on until today, what has
been the most consistent source of
conflict, violence, suffering, death,
uh, refugees, and basically in a word
instability? It has been the existence
of the state of Israel. And it's always
painted in a way as well, the Arabs hate
us, the Arabs try to kill us, so we have
to, but that's of course that's that's
the myth. The reality is it has been a
source of instability and by design. In
other words, the Zionists very early on,
the very very early leadership of the
Zionist after the state was created was
to always maintain instability around
them and that is how they project power
and that is how they project influence
and that's what they've been doing. So
why would they attack Iran again? Again,
why attack Iran to begin with? You know,
Iran supports the Palestinians. Iran
does not will not bow down to the empire
and so on. Same with Yemen. Um, but why
now? Why bomb them again? Why bomb them
at all? Why? And again, the the what we
saw in the last attack on Iran, Israelis
are vulnerable. Israel is very
vulnerable. I mean, these attacks the
the the the um the attacks back from
Iran, the uh you know, were severe. I
mean, they really crippled Israel and
people were terrified and people are
already terrified because of uh October
7. there. There's no way to make sense
of any of it other than this idea that
Israel must maintain instability in the
region.
>> I want to ask you about that
vulnerability.
The conventional wisdom last month was
that the Israelis stopped bombing not
because they were done or they had
accomplished their military goals, but
because they were running short on
missiles. Do you think that's changed?
Ha. Has the US been able to supply
Israel with whatever missiles it needs
for a second go with uh with the
Iranians? And do you think the Iranians
would be able to retaliate like they did
last time?
>> I mean, I didn't have any more
information than anybody else on that. I
assume that they that they uh I assume
that they're always able to uh to fill
in whatever it is that they use. And so,
I don't think there's a problem there.
America is more than willing to supply
Israel with as much as many arms and
ammunition as it wants. Um I think I
mean I don't I don't have again any
information about Iranian capabilities
but my sense is that we have not seen
that Iran has always if we look at it
historically since this you know tension
with the US and Israel has been going
on. Iran has always opted for um being
responsible,
you know, being restrained,
not going all out. And I've seen we've
seen this throughout. I mean, we've seen
this throughout. It's been going on for
for decades.
>> I think they even called it strategic
patience.
>> Yeah, it makes sense. And that's I
believe that's what they're doing. I
think that's it's it's the responsible
thing to do. And that's why we haven't
seen an all-out war. That's why the
region is still standing. And it's not
all in you know dro totally destroyed I
mean the region between you know Iran
and Palestine otherwise the whole place
would have been in in complete ruins. So
who knows I mean I I I I don't know what
the Iranian capabilities are but my
sense is that what we saw
uh last time was only the tip of the
iceberg. I think there's a lot more that
they could do if they chose to do so.
which makes you wonder even more why it
why the Israeli government would want to
attack them.
>> What do you think a second Israeli
attack on Iran would mean for the
Russians and the Chinese? It it seems to
me that there would be a great chance of
the whole thing spinning out of control
or
are the Russians just too bogged down in
Ukraine or dealing with their own
issues? The Chinese have this long
history of non-intervention.
Do you think there's a possibility that
a second Israeli attack on Iran could
bring in these superpowers or am I
looking into this too too much?
>> I don't know. I mean Putin said recently
that um he is staying away from you know
intervening with these in these things
because Israel has such a large Russian
population. after the fall of the Soviet
Union, about a million uh Russians
immigrated. Many of them, some were
Jews, some were not so Jewish, but the
point is that they're there. And you
know, there are cities that you walk
around and all you see is Russians and
all you hear is Russia. I mean, you
know, they're they're significant and
they're voting block and so on. And he
the way he described it I was surprised
but the way he described it was that he
has a sense of responsibility for these
people and for Israel because of the
large Russian population that is there.
Um that's might be an excuse. I don't
know. So I don't see him intervening. Uh
and China like you say you never know. I
mean you wish that they would because I
think that could tip the scale. I think
that could bring about more restraint uh
on Israel.
um as long as businesses as usual,
Israel wouldn't stop. So, one would hope
that China and Russia, you know, the the
the bricks the BRICS alliance would
intervene. We wish they would intervene
in the genocide in Gaza, but for reasons
for some reason they don't. None of them
do. And I think it's very sad that they
don't.
Israel announced earlier this week that
it is considering the forcible removal
of all Gaza Palestinians who don't leave
uh Gaza on their own accord, moving them
all to South Sudan, which is arguably
the worst place on earth. This is of
course the very definition of ethnic
cleansing. And look at it this way. It
would be
I'm going to use the word even if it's
controversial. It would be a ghetto
moving all of these Palestinians
to a place that they have no connection
to and forcing them to stay there. Is
this a serious proposal on the part of
the Israelis? Because it's so badly
illegal that it makes me wonder how in
the world it would be implemented. What
do you think?
>> It's not realistic. Um, you know, you
could offer them to move to Hawaii and
they still want and Palestinians still
won't leave. Um, and so but what so I I
I don't think there's a chance in hell
that it's going to be implemented. I
think what what is troublesome is the
nonchalantness
of how this is being reported. I mean I
there was a piece in AP yesterday and
they just reported as you know and the
terminology they use is like all these
you know just just very benign terms
relocation and resettlement. We're
talking about a plan. We're talking
about major figures, you know, within
these governments,
Israel, the Egyptians, uh the Americans,
perhaps the South Sudin who are talking
about committing a massive crime against
humanity of unbelievable proportions.
You know, unbelievable proportions.
We're talking about forcibly remove
trying to remove two million people and
again not even just to a different part
of their own country or their continents
to a whole other continent.
>> I mean whatever place with no food and
no water and no infrastructure and no
medical care
>> impoverished and torn by war and we're
we're we're not talking about sheep.
We're not talking about cattle. We're
talking about human beings. Now, a large
percentage, as you know, of the people
who live in the Gaza ghetto, and it's
already it's it's gone beyond a ghetto.
It's it's a death camp right now. But a
large percentage of those people are
already have been displaced from other
places in Palestine. In other words,
they're already refugees. So, they've
been displaced from other parts of
Palestine. They've been living in this
ghetto for almost eight decades. Now,
they're talking and again, they report
on it as so nonchalantly like it's Yeah.
Well, you know, we're just talking about
removing, you know, uh, resettling
people. What are you talking about
moving at two million people or even if
it was less, if it were a thousand
people? It doesn't matter to a whole new
continent just because Israel wants the
land. Just because these group of
racist, violent settlers took over
Palestine and they don't want to see
Palestinians there anymore. I mean, it's
insane. It's absolutely insane. The
solution for the question of pal of of
Gaza is not removing it's not even
humanitarian aid. It's liberation of
Palestine. It's liberating the
concentration camp just like was done
after World War II. Certainly the
millions of people in camps during World
War II needed humanitarian aid. But the
goal was liberation. They had to be
liberated and the regime that put them
there had to be removed. That applies to
Palestine now. We should be talking
about liberation. this idea and it seems
so farfetched, but liberation and the
right of return, these are the terms.
These are the these are the demands that
need to be made um across the board
beyond anything else.
>> Yeah. And this puts the the Egyptians
and the Jordanians in such a bad spot.
Fully half the population of Jordan is
ethnically Palestinian.
Generations and generations of refugees.
Uh, and then Egypt, as much as the
Egyptian people might want to open the
border to help their Palestinian
brothers, they know that they can't
because that would be abetting the
Israelis in their forced removal of
Palestinians. And so they're stuck.
They're all stuck between Iraq and a
hard place. You know, we've we've heard
about Israeli ideas to move the
Palestinians to Albania, for example.
They said, "Oh, it's already a Muslim
country. We just send them all to
Albania." And then the Albanians said
literally, "Hey, nobody mentioned this
to us. We're not going to take 2 million
uh people. We're one of the poorest
countries uh in the hemisphere." And
then we heard, "Well, there's this
island off the coast of Indonesia. We
can put them all there." No, they're not
going to send everybody to Indonesia.
They can't go to Jordan. They can't go
to Egypt. Maybe it's because they
shouldn't be going anywhere. maybe they
should be just secure in their own homes
and on their own property, but nobody
wants to talk about that.
>> You know, I think it's what makes it
even more more uh disturbing is that
these are Jewish it's it's the so-called
Jewish state that's planting this
planting this talking. In other words,
these are Jewish people who know what
happened to Jews in World War II and and
claiming that this is somehow to protect
Jewish people that are talking about
crimes that are equal, if not worse,
than what the Nazis did. You know, I
think you know this. I've, you know, in
my entire career of speaking and and so
on, I never make comparison to the
Nazis. But how the it's it's it's
impossible not to. We have a
concentration camp, which is Gaza. weed.
It's become a death camp. There's
starvation and and the most worst
torture one can imagine. Resources are
abundant outside the camp, but they're
not letting people have access to the
resources. I mean, Palestine is a rich
country. There's no lack of resources
there, but they're keeping them in
there. And they're talking about
bringing aid from across the world
through through Egypt. I mean, it's it
none of this makes any sense. And these
are Jewish people that are claiming, you
know, all these claims about the
Holocaust and how, you know, the
terrible things that were happened to
Jewish people and these and this is what
they're doing. This is what the
so-called Jewish state is planning. And
the world, like you said, the world is
just, yeah, let's go along with it. Why
not? I mean, you know, who let's move
them to. Are you are we what are we are
we out of our minds? Are we even allow
this conversation to continue?
>> We shouldn't even have the conversation.
That's right.
>> You're exactly right.
should be reported as an attempt to
commit a a a
horrific crime of massive proportions
and instead it's being reported as well
just news. There's these plans out
there. I I'll it's beyond understanding
really. Mika, like you, all my life,
I've been very very reticent, very
reluctant to compare anything to the
Nazis just because of the horrors uh
that the Nazis inflicted um on on
everybody, everybody that they
encountered. But you're right, there are
so many parallels now. I mean, ovens
aside, look at the parallels. We're
talking about ghettos. We're talking
about starvation. We're talking about
forced removal. We're talking about
wanted murder. I mean, you're just
standing in line uh waiting for, you
know, a a a handful of of grain or
something that you can try to to gain
some nourishment from. And then the IDF
just opens fire on the people waiting in
line. There's no clean water. There's no
medical care. They've flattened all of
the hospitals. Now they're going to go
back into Gaza City and finish
flattening that. And we would be we
would be wrong to not draw comparisons
at this point.
>> Yeah. Yeah. You know, I mean, where
where do you where do you even start? I
mean, they're they're planning they the
the the Israeli cabinet just voted to
commit four divisions. So that's
somewhere between 80 and 100,000 troops
to go in and take the city of Gaza.
You wonder what what I mean what first
of all it's all destroyed. What else?
What is there for these troops to do
other than kill more people? You know,
they're estimating about people living
in the city of Gaza around it. And it's
they say, "Well, we want to push them
back. You want to push them south. You
want to do this. You want to do that."
And the world is just, you know, sitting
there. I mean, yeah, granted, you know,
there's been some condemnation. Uh,
Norway did a few things. Other countries
were saying things, but it's it's it's
beyond belief. It's absolutely beyond
belief that this is going on. And now,
and I think it's important to remember
that the ghettos the the Gaza Strip,
so-called Gaza Strip, has been a ghetto
from the very beginning, since it was
established in, you know, the early 50s.
But there are other ghettos. The West
Bank is now just a bunch of different
ghettos. Palestinians who live in 1948
also live in ghettos. They can't go and
live somewhere else. They have more
freedom, but they don't have complete,
they can't choose where they live, where
they work, where they go to school. You
know what I mean? They live within
limitations, um, very severe limitations
as though they were in a ghetto. And
this is the reality that Palestinians
have had to endure for almost 100 years.
It's insane. And the world is just
allowing this mythology that somehow the
Jews are allowed to do this
because of the Holocaust or because of
this or because of that. It makes it it
not only makes no sense, but it is a
kind of cruelty that is beyond
understanding.
I I want to ask you too about domestic
Israeli politics.
Netanyahu, despite the fact that he's
the longest serving prime minister in
Israeli history, has never been
universally popular. In fact, his liker
has never garnered more than something
like 27%.
All the governments of course are
coalition governments. has to patch
together. This one is exceptionally
rightwing, but what what is Israeli
public opinion right now on these
internal military moves? Has has this
war um or invasion, it's not even really
a war if only one side is armed. Has
this Gaza situation
rescued him politically? Or are there
Israelis who think like you do that this
is wrong wrong wrong wrong wrong and
they've got to come to some sort of of
agreement
what divides Israeli society is whether
you like or hate Netanyahu that's
basically the division
like you said his his ability to create
coalition governments is the way he's
been able to survive this long as prime
minister even when he other parties had
more seats than him he still became
prime minister because he knows he's the
horse trader. He's the best and he's
really the best politician. He's, you
know, he's like he's the he's really the
only adult in the room when it comes to
Israeli politics. Nobody can nobody can
beat him. And so um so but but in terms
of Israeli society, so you've got he's
got about 55% that are with him and
maybe 45% that are against him. And
that's been the split all along. In
terms of in terms of the genocide,
there's very broad support for the
genocide in Gaza. The question is, do we
pause
to somehow allow the uh hostages to
return or do we go full blast and not
worry about the hostages? And again,
that goes the split is about the same.
the people that are with it anyhow are
okay with what he's just government just
decided to do and the people against him
are against it and they want to see the
hostages returned first. What's also
interesting is that the uh you know that
they just they they just nom you know
they fired the previous army chief staff
and now they brought in this new guy
which is supposed to be like a you know
a great you know great leader whatever
whatever you know and now he opposed
this plan to go in with four divisions
and take the city of Gaza and he even
said if that's what you want to do then
scrap the the release of the hostages is
one of the goals forget that that's
that's not going to happen. Um, so now
the go so now members of the cabinet are
going against him and calling for his
removal.
And it's very interesting to see that
because you know, Israelis are very very
involved in in the military far more
than any other any other people that I
know. I mean, how many people down the
street know who the chairman of the
joint chiefs is in in this country or
the chief of staff of whatever and
nobody knows these things, right? The
general of this zero that Israelis are
so in tune to this. They're like they
know all this stuff. And so now this is
happening as well that the government is
turning against this new army chief of
staff which they just nominated and they
just uh approved. So uh you know I I
think I think Israel society is is
really completely being torn at the
seams. It's falling apart. But that's a
whole other that's a whole other issue.
But in terms of the genocide, in terms
when it comes to the land, when it comes
to the state, when it comes to the
Palestinians,
this has been the strength of the
Zionists from, you know, going back more
than 100 years. On those issues, they
always unite. On those issues, there are
no divisions. They put their divisions
aside. And this is and I think it it
shows that the weakness of our side of
the of the of those who stand for
justice and and freedom in Palestine is
that we don't have that ability to put
our differences aside and work together
for liberation. And I think that's one
of our that's our main weakness. But in
terms of the Zionists, that is why they
were able to within 50 years of the
invention of Zionism practically to have
a state, a Jewish state against all odds
with a minority population with, you
know, with really very little resources.
They had a state within 50 years, which
is remarkable, you know, but it's
because on the issue of the land, the
state, and the Arabs, there's always
unity.
You know, I was watching an old uh video
of President Harry Truman. This was on
YouTube just a few days ago. And Truman
was giving this address to the nation
and he was announcing the creation of
the state of Israel and the US
recognition of Israel. And he said that
um he he knew that he had succeeded
because both the Israelis and the
Palestinians hated him at the end of the
negotiations. So he's declaring
declaring victory and and moving on. But
one of the things that he said was
fascinating to me. It was that the US
and other major countries, I think the
Russians were second, recognized the
state of Israel on that night in 1948.
And that recognition of a Palestinian
state would come uh following additional
negotiations.
That was 1948
and we're still waiting for a
Palestinian state. Do you think that any
of the major Western countries, and I'm
going to talk about them in a second, do
you think any of them are serious about
the creation of a Palestinian state?
>> No. I know for a there's there's no
question that none of them are serious
about it. That's why we need to be
serious about it. You know, the only way
first of all, I I I want to redefine
some of the some of the terms. I would I
would argue that the name of the country
is Palestine.
Israel is a regime that has taken over.
>> Yeah, it's a good point.
>> This kind of came up a little bit with
the, you know, with uh when Israel was
attacking Iran, they always refer to
Iran as a regime. And I'm like, no, Iran
is a country we you like don't like the
government. That's whole other issue,
but it's an Iranian issue. Um, when it
comes to Palestine, Palestine is the
country and Israel is the regime. It's a
regime that needs to be taken out. It's
a regime that has taken over Palestine
and has been destroying it. And so the
idea of having the state of Israel
recognized and postponing the liberation
of Palestine that has been a very
successful campaign and when we look at
what has been what has been the focus on
Palestine at least from the largely from
the west aid uh you know relief all
these NOS's popping up to take care of
the poor refugees to take care of this
to take care of that and it has imagine
if all those millions if billions of
dollars and all the working hours of
people and the staff and the offices and
the buildings and all this
infrastructure all this NGO
infrastructure that's been invested
imagine if all of these resources were
put into liberation
but what happened was it drained
liberation became a bad word liberation
was was was associated with terrorism
liberation was associated with
anti-semitism and all that kind of stuff
and so all the effort have gone and And
you see some of these NGOs's, they're
enormous. And they got more money now,
especially now, than they know what to
do with. And they're popping up. New new
new relief organizations for Gaza are
popping up every day. We cannot help the
people in Gaza. They won't let the food
in. There's nothing we can do. If you
want to help the people of Gaza,
liberate them so they can have access to
the resources. But imagine if all of
those resources over the decades and
decades and decades since 1948 have been
had been invested in liberating
Palestine. We wouldn't be here today. we
wouldn't be talking about this.
Palestine would have been liberated. It
would have it would have been free by
now. And I think that is that is just
just an incredibly important point for
people to come to terms with. We need to
talk about liberation. That is the way
out of the problem that we have. But
because there's a crisis and our natural
inclination when there's a crisis to try
to fix the crisis, we can't fix this
crisis without fixing the whole thing.
You know, there's never going to be a
Palestinian state unless Palestine is
liberated and it's becomes and the land
that is called Palestine also has a
state that is called Palestine and what
it should be called. You know, the story
that's the name of the country, that
should be the name of the state. But
again, the West is going back to
two-state solution and all these things
they know are never going to happen
because it's safe and they support aid
and they support relief because it's
safe and also because it drains. It
really does drain the the the you know
the efforts for liberation because the
the the these NGOs's pay a salary and
these NOS's take away people who have
come out and they have no other jobs and
they open up possibilities and they
bring some development. So people
naturally gravitate that way and are
taken away from the struggle for
liberation and they're not even allowed
to talk about it when you're working for
these. They don't even want you to talk
about these things and that's a serious
problem. So that's where the west is and
I think it's going to stay that way
unless we are able to bring about the
change.
>> Well, along those same lines, the UK,
France, Canada, Australia, New Zealand,
handful of other countries said that
they would recognize Palestine in
September. September presumably because
of the start of the UN General Assembly,
unless the Israelis take concrete steps
to end the the siege of Gaza, that's not
going to happen. So assuming that these
major western countries recognize
Palestine and and frankly the rest of
the world already has it's just the West
that's the hold out. So assuming that
this diplomatic recognition happens
what exactly would that mean? Would it
change anything anything on the ground?
>> No. It's a great it's a great thing to
do because it's meaningless.
>> Yeah.
>> And so and cost anything
>> well it doesn't cost anything. It
doesn't do anything. It doesn't change
anything. And so it's safe. That's why
all these governments around the world
opted to. Their constituents are
demanding they do something to
Palestine. They don't want to. They're
afraid to. They can't. Whatever the
reason may be in every particular
country. So they say, "Well, we're going
to recognize Palestinian state." What
does that mean? That means you have a
building with a guy sitting there who
happens to be called an ambassador. It
means nothing. They have no power. They
have no They have nothing. If they
wanted to do something significant
like they would unrecognize Israel, they
would kick out the diplomatic missions,
the Israeli diplomatic missions. They
would impose sanctions. That's
recognizing Palestine. Recognizing that
Palestine has been taken over by a
vicious racist regime. That is
meaningful.
>> And that's what happened with South
Africa in the 1980s. It it wasn't just
that countries, you know,
attempted to recognize, you know, the
ANC, let's say, as the as the legitimate
uh representative of of the South
African people, they they withdrew
diplomatic recognition of South Africa
and the government collapsed.
>> And if you hosted an event, any event,
academic, athletic, sporting event,
whatever event, and you invited a South
African team, you would be penalized. In
other words, it was that severe, that
severe. And then, you know, I have a
friend who was on the board of Palestine
House Freedom and um he was involved in
the anti-aparttheide movement in
Connecticut and they managed to get the
state of Connecticut in 1981
to uh boycott uh South Africa.
>> So, in other words,
>> 81.
>> Yeah.
>> Well, that was early.
>> That was very early and it took several
years. It took a lot of work to do. So
I'm saying, you know, that there was a
real movement and of course, you know,
there was a lot of support. I mean, you
know, the there was the Soviet Union,
there was Cuba, there were a lot of, you
know, serious powers that worked to
support the anti-apartid movement and
the liberation of of South Africa. We we
don't have that right now. Everybody is
working with Israel. Everybody is
supporting Israel for whatever reason.
So we don't have like an ANC or the
South African Communist Party that were
major players that man managed to really
you know great great people that were
working within this within this uh
leadership. Uh and again because
liberation is considered a bad word.
Return is considered unacceptable.
We we we don't have that. We don't even
have anybody talking about these things.
And that's a shortcut. That's that's the
problem. That's the in in comparison
between the two cases, South Africa and
Palestine. That is the weakness. That is
our weakness.
>> You alluded to something when we first
started talking um today about the uh
the West Bank. The American mainstream
media are just now, and I mean like in
the last week, beginning to cover the
violence that's currently taking place
in the West Bank. And by violence, I'm
talking about armed Jewish settlers
attacking Palestinian villages
wholesale. They're killing residents.
They're seizing their properties. One of
the last remaining Christian villages,
Palestinian villages in the West Bank
just a couple of weeks ago went to the
settlers.
Do you see a change in the US media
toward the broader conflict?
And and forgive me if I'm trying to
influence your response. I'm not trying
to influence your response, but it just
seems to me that anti-Palestinian
violence, whether it's on the part of
the IDF or the settlers or the average
Israeli in the street, has become so bad
that it's just impossible to ignore
anymore if you are the Associated Press
or the Washington Post or the New York
Times. And I'm wondering if if this
change in attitude among the US media is
toward the broader conflict or is this
coverage situational in that they just
can't ignore it. Ignore it when all this
violence is taking place. What do you
think? Are we seeing a change or is this
just temporary?
>> No, I don't think we're seeing a change.
I think what we're seeing is um an
attempt to just um
calm people down and say, you look, we
were reporting about it. We're saying
something about it. You know, the New
York Times just interviewed
Zakaria Zve who's
really well-known Palestinian local uh
you know, leader. He was a you know,
he's got a whole history. I New York
Times just interviewed in Zakaria's B.
That's like huge. you know, he was
leader of this uh um of the resistance
as a kid. He really became very famous
with uh the Janine Theater. Later on, if
you remember there was this escape from
uh prison, six guys escaped and he was
the leader of that. Anyway, he's a
really well-known and highly respected
and I'm going wow New York Times has
interviewed him. Wow. You know, but they
only interviewed him to show that he's
broken.
They interviewed him to show that he's
hopeless. you know, he lost his son also
in in one of the latest uh attacks on
Janine. So, it's it's it's it's
horrifying. The problem is again is that
there's not a holistic approach to
reporting on this. Attacks by Zionists
against innocent Palestinian bystanders
has has has been going on since the
early 20th century.
I mean Zionist terrorism I mean Zionist
brought terrorism to to Palestine and
Zionist terrorism has been has been you
know
an issue with Palestine is terrorizing
Palestine you know since then now you're
recognizing that there's a problem it's
been going on consistently and it is a
policy it's not like a random act of a
few crazy people who went and burned a
village no look at this look look at the
last hundred years in of what
Palestinians have been living through
the Zionist terrorism. And again,
sometimes it's militia, sometimes it's a
citizen, sometimes it's somebody who, I
don't know, had an issue. It doesn't
really matter, but it's systemic. And
the problem is that nobody, and again,
goes back to the issue of liberation.
There's this uh this desire to never
show that this is systemic. They're
afraid to show that this is systemic,
that the ethnic cleansing is systemic,
the genocide is systemic, the attacks on
Palestinians, the terrorizing
Palestinians, the terrorism that is
inflicted on Palestinians on a daily
basis everywhere in Palestine is
systemic. It's part of a plan. It's
called ethnic cleansing. That's what
this is. It's not only about putting
people in trucks and moving them. It's
also creating living conditions that are
impossible. And they're taking over
villages and they're taking over
monuments. They just took over. They
just, you know, the the religious the
the the religious um the important
religious uh monuments in Palestine are
usually run by um by by the Muslim
trust. It's called the walks. Uh one of
the most if not probably the second most
important uh Islamic uh monument and
Islamic site in Palestine is the mosque
in Hebron. It's one of the four or five
most important Islamic um uh sites in
the world and they just handed it over
from the what it was a gradual process
over the years but they just handed over
control of it to the settlers you know
there are there are parts of the mosque
there that were created when Salahadin
was you know by Salah I mean it's
historically an incredible and the
settlers have been coming and
desecrating it the you know for for
decades it's been a long story but now
officially. Now, who knows about the
mosque? A few people. Most people don't.
Who reported on this? Hardly anyone.
Nobody knows how important this is. The
next step is Alaka being handed over to
the settlers. There's no question about
that. There's already already the
heization of Alaka is taking place. This
is happening all the time and nobody's
reporting about this. Nobody's reporting
about this this um you know what what is
basically a takeover of all of Palestine
by Israel and the elimination of the
history of the religion of everything
else that is that is um that is
Palestinian or Muslim or Arab in
Palestine.
>> One last substantive question for you
Miko. Um just this past week the
Israelis killed a reporter and four
support staff uh from Al Jazzer. This is
a a long-standing pattern. The Israelis,
it seems like they enjoy killing uh
journalists. Uh I'm still thinking about
Shireen Abu Akla, who was wearing a
bulletproof vest that said press, a
Kevlar helmet that said press, and an
Israeli sniper shot her in the face, and
then the IDF disrupted her funeral, made
the pawbearers drop the the coffin right
there in the church. It was just a
disaster. But one of the reasons why I'm
so upset about all this is just today I
read an article saying that the Israeli
government has never prosecuted
anybody in the death of any journalist
ever. Now Netanyahu said I think it was
yesterday that well there will be an
investigation. He always says that
there's always some pretend
investigation.
I'm assuming that this is an Israeli
government policy to murder journalists.
Um, if that's the case,
why don't they just come clean with it
and say, "Look, you know, we don't
respect international journalism. You
take your life into your hands if you're
coming in here. Uh, we may kill you and
maybe it's going to be on purpose and
maybe it's going to be by accident." I
mean, why play this game?
>> They kind of do say it. They kind of do
say it. I mean, you know, they kind of
do say it because we we have a history.
You know, I remember when Shirley was
murdered, there was a question of uh you
know, they were still discussing an
accident and it turned out it was a
sniper. Okay, a sniper on his own
would not do something like that without
the backing. And the local commander
wouldn't take that responsibility
either. The killing of Sharina Blay had
to come from the very very top of the
Israeli government. Otherwise, they
would not have dared to do something
like this. So, there's no question that
there's a policy and there's and they
kind of do say, well, you know, if
you're going to come in there, you're on
your own here. We can't guarantee your
safety kind of thing. But they do say,
you know, you're you're we're going to
kill you. We don't want you in there. We
don't want you to report you. You're
you're And then they make they mask it.
They said that he was um that Anus was a
leader of Hamasil in Isra in the Hebrew
nose. They're claiming that the, you
know, the international media is
anti-Semitic because he was actually, we
have information that he was a leader of
Hamas.
>> Outrageous.
>> That's outrageous. But they do they do
kind of say it and and and God bless
these journalists and these people that
go in there anyway to do it. I mean,
they are true heroes.
>> Yeah, you can say that again.
>> So, last question for you and this is
this is the same question that I ask you
every time we speak.
Is there any reason at all to be
optimistic?
>> Well, I think in the I think in the long
run, yes, of course. I think we see
Israeli society falling apart. I think
uh the aftermath of October 7th has been
the you know that there's been a
paralysis in the state of Israel. The
apartheid state is still in the state of
of chaos. paralysis. His society is in a
state of chaos like never before. People
are at each other's throat. The economy
is not doing well thanks to the Yemeni
forces. The port of Elat, which as you
know is an very important port has
completely shut down. Um
more and more uh countries are and and
not just countries but unions and so
forth are are are refusing to uh to work
with with ships or planes that go to
Israel and that sort of thing. So I
think in the long term yes and I think
and I think that um I think that the
fall of the apartheid state and the
creation the liberation of Palestine
is upon us without any question and I
think we should not lose hope you know
not even for one second. I think we need
to maintain that um that vision of a
liberated Palestine
and and the cost obviously is is
horrendous. But even with that, we need
to to have that vision, you know, in our
mind constantly every single day, every
single moment so that we fight for it
and that we see that vision becoming a
reality. But I think hope is not
something that we have uh the luxury to
give up on. author and activist Miko
Pelid. Real quickly, tell us about the
uh the Palestine House of Freedom.
>> Sure, happy to. Um, we established it,
we opened it a little over a year ago as
a space for Palestine, unapologetically
Palestine. Our mission as a nonprofit is
education and our purpose is to educate,
to demonstrate through education, that
the vision of a liberated Palestine is
is is a is is a good thing. It's a
hopeful thing. It's the only really way
to move beyond the violence and the
instability. If you want to see
stability and peace and so forth, then
removing the apartheid regime and
allowing a free democratic Palestine
with equal rights to take its place is
the way to go. And that's problem is the
pe where in this country everybody's
invested in the obstacle to peace in the
obstacle to stability which is the
apartheid state. Um and we have events
constantly. We show movies, we have
panels, we have speakers, we have
community events all the time. Uh we're
working with other groups uh outside of
the Palestine issue as well in
collaboration. And so we've um we're
we're we're there. We have proudly
display the Palestinian flag on
Pennsylvania Avenue as you've seen
>> on
seen it there too.
>> We do that. That's who and it's
palestinasfreedom.org
if anybody wants to go check us out.
>> Excellent. I've been there. It's a
beautiful facility and I I would
encourage people to check it out as
well. So, Miko, thanks so much for
joining us and thanks to our viewers for
joining us. Please do us that favor of
hitting like and share and most
importantly subscribe. We'll bring you
more great programming. Have a great
day.